kylebatson@hey.com

(316) 990-4246

phone

# Kyle Batson UX/UI Designer

### **Profile**

Senior UX designer with extensive experience in front-end development and accessibility. I enjoy understanding how systems work and learning how to make complexity seem simple to delight the user. I am passionate about the quality of the products I work on and advocating for the needs of the user in every stage of product development. I have also led software engineering teams so I am proficient at communicating about the design process with non-designers.

## **Experience**

2018-present

### America's Job Link Alliance, Senior UX Designer

- » Responsible for the UX/UI, user research, and front-end development of a workforce/ job board/case management application for use in 9 U.S. States
- » Performed user interviews/testing to incorproate user goals into feature design
- » Created reusable semantic and accessible templates, components, stylesheets for application development
- » Responsible for WCAG 2.1 AA accessibility conformance evaluations

### 2015-2017 |

### **Educational Testing Service,** UX/UI Design Team Manager

- » Managed team of 5 including UX designers, web designers, front-end developers, and accessibility specialists responsible for the UX/UI of a suite of web applications used to administer and deliver secure, reliable assessments to K-12 students in multiple states across the United States
- » Formalized design process and integrations with other departments including business analysts, software developers, project managers, software testers, and support staff with a focus on user-centered design and advocacy
- » Promoted universal design practices and accessibility considerations at every stage of the development process

#### 2013-2015

### **Computerized Assessments & Learning, Software Developer Team Lead**

- » Promoted to directed the design of the application both on the front-end and its integration with the back-end which delivered assessments for over 5 million K-12 students around the US and internationally
- » Managed the the workload and development priorities for a team of 7 with product managers and stakeholders for on-time delivery
- » Assisted in the design of the system's JSON-based data format and developed parsing rules from XML input
- » Promoted a modular and configurable application design to allow for both multitenant use and easy customization for various client needs
- » Assisted in requirements gathering and created extensive documentation of features

### 2011-2013 |

### Computerized Assessments & Learning, Interaction Designer

- » Designed a highly-configurable UI for a K-12 assessment delivery system to deliver assessments in multiple languages
- » Developed product's HTML templates and CSS to ensure proper separation of markup and presentation
- Developed interactions across mouse, touch, and keyboard navigation interfaces with a mobile-first approach to support multiple device types and oprating systems
- » Designed and developed Javascript-based mini-assessments

### **Skills**

- » User Experience Design
- » Wireframing and Prototyping
- » Information Architecture
- » Front-end Development
- » Responsive Design
- » Semantic Markup
- Accessibility Conformance
- » Team Management
- » Agile Scrum
- » Graphic Design
- » Branding and Identity Design

### **Tools**

- Graphic Design: Photoshop, Illustrator, InDesign
- » Wireframing/Prototyping: Axure, Adobe XD
- » Front End: HTML5, CSS3, SASS/LESS, Javascript, jQuery, Bootstrap, Foundation
- » Back End: Ruby on Rails, PHP, JSON, MySQL
- » Version Control: Git
- » Content Mangement: ExpressionEngine, WordPress

### **Education**

**University of Kansas**BFA Visual Communications

# Experience continued...

2008present **Premier Sports Management,** Web Designer and Web Developer (contractor)

- » Website design and development of various websites for Premier Sports Management
- » Design and development of a web application for public voting on student athletes including voting system, data
- » submission and data export features
- » Design and development of a web application to scrape baseball stats and present an ongoing ranking of player value

2006-present |

#### Freelance, Graphic Design, Web Development, Photography

Worked with many clients to create or improve their online presence through:

- » Branding and identity work
- » Website design
- » Full-stack website development and contentent management system integration with ExpressionEngine and WordPress
- » Architectural and product photography

2009-2009 |

#### OnTarget Interactive, Web Designer/Web Developer, Graphic Designer

- » Designed multiple client websites and integrated into ExpressionEngine and Drupal content management systems
- » Worked with the team to create product branding and collateral for clients
- » Product photography and print advertisement design
- » Print design for catalogs in Adobe InDesign

2006-2007 |

### University of Kansas, Web Designer/Developer

- » Responsible for standards-based front-end site development and developed a simple CMS in PHP, MySQL to improve ease-of-use in updating the Department of Fine Arts website
- » Worked with a cross-disciplinary team (physicists, illustrators, developers and designers) to develop educational games for kids in HTML/Javascript as well as Flash/Actionscript

### References

### Kalyana Koka

Director of R&D at ETS (785) 312-0389 kkoka@ets.org

#### **Joy Bancroft**

Customer Experience Manager at AJLA-TS (913) 484-6086 joybancroft@gmail.com

#### **Christine Panus**

Owner of Panus Ventures (785) 760-4466 christine.panus@gmail.com